A Guide to the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA) FA079
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Photographs, 1946-1968, n.d.; 19.0 Boxes
  - Venezuela
    - CBR, Andean Study (Box 8, Folder 157)
      1. The only Venezuelan wheat is grown on the temperate Andean slopes, and CBR economists have found that it seldom is a moneymaking crop. The farmers usually consume the flour themselves, paying for having it ground at primitive mills, such as the one shown, with a portion of the crop. 2. Brick and tile kilns are of various types and shapes as they exist in areas where clay products are fired in the Andes. Pictured is a relatively large kiln with fire box below the area where brick and tile are placed. 3. Generation of electricity has increased in the Andes during recent years. But most of the increase has been accomplished in small motor driven plants few of which are as large as the plant shown here at Valera. 4. A drug store located on the main street of the town of Santo Domingo, in the State of Merida is shown in this picture. In this store are sold not only medicinal products but also other articles of basic necessities. This lack of commercial specialization is characteristic of the small business establishments which are the predominant type in the Andean region. 5. Vegetables can be grown in the Andes in some areas and especially where irrigation water is available with a good comparative advantage over low tropical areas as far as quality and quantity of production is concerned. The better valley bottom soils could well be used for this purpose with good possibilities of reasonable economic return for the high labor and other cost input required for vegetables. 6. An illegal distillery of rudimentary construction, which was confiscated by the National Guards near Banco de Barinas in the southeast part of Tachira is shown in this picture. In the Andean region there are foreigners who try to augment their income through this illegal activity. In 1952, in the State of Tachira only, 836 illegal distilleries were discovered with an estimated average production of 40 meters per unit. 7. Pasture maintenance practices in many areas of the Andes still call for annual burning of old grasses as shown here above Palmira in Tachira. Considerable work is necessary in carrying out experiments in technological methods and in demonstrating improved practices to farmers so that unit productivity can be increased and destructive resource use diminished. 8. Very careful soil conservational practices are needed, including contour planting, strip cropping with permanent sod crops and other practices, for safe use of land with 30% slope as that pictured in the left hand side of this photo. An annual crop of field peas is shown. 9. Vegetable farming methods in the Andes still call for the use of the wooden plow and oxen for plowing. This field in Tachira in which a crop of cabbage and cauliflower had already been produced during the year was being prepared for a second crop of tomatoes and carrots. Some farmers attempt triple cropping during a season in this area. 10. The hand tools typically used in annual crop farm areas as well as most other types of farming are shown here. Notice the heavy "palas" leaned up against the box which are used both for digging and hoeing. The wedge shaped piece of metal on the box to the right of the shovel handle is an iron plow tip for use on the wooden plows. A few farmers use such tips but most plows are all wood. Notice the absence of the light type garden hoe which is easier to use than the heavy hoes and palas pictured for many hand operations in tilling crops. 11. Production of sugar cane on steep hillside areas in the Andes is common. However, most agronomists and cost conscious farmers believe that such production is uneconomic because of low yields and extra expenses of land preparation and harvesting on slope areas. Sugar cane does best on the level riverside areas where irrigation water is available and some mechanization of field operations can be accomplished. 12. Annual crops planted regularly on slopes as steep as that shown for the corn in this picture can do little else than destroy the top soil available. This slope is about 80 percent and it is common to see such steep slopes used for annual crops in the Andes. 13. Old style vertically mounted presses for extracting sugar cane juice are still found in use, especially on farms where the juice is used for guarapo rather than panels. Commercial producers of sugar cane usually have machine powered trapiches available. 14. Part of the dwellings are utilized for the limited processing of annual crops as shown here for tobacco. Seldom are special sheds facilities constructed for better control of the processing operations for any annual crops. 15. Livestock farmers ordinarily have to deliver their cattle for sale at central market areas. Buyers seldom come to the ranch to complete sales. Cattle are shown here en route over a jungle trail to a highway where they will be trucked to San Cristobal for sale. 16. The straight type "pala" is used most frequently for the hoeing vegetables. Shown here is a farmer hoeing and hilling up onions in the Flor Marin area of Tachira. 17. The wooden plow as pictured here is still used almost exclusively on annual crop farms and vegetable farms throughout the Andes. These plows will last two or three years when used for plowing three or four hectares per year. Two oxen are used to pull them. The steep slopes cultivated by Andean farmers preclude the use of any buy hand-wielded implements. 18. The Andean area is dependent on the Llanos areas for most of the livestock fattened or kept for dairy cows in the mountain areas. The picture shows a herd of cattle being driven through the Uribante valley en route to fattening zones in Tachira. 19. Planting sticks (coas) are used most frequently for planting corn and beans and some other crops on annual crop farms. Shown here is a man planting beans. Often two men work at planting. The first makes the hole with the stick and the second places the seeds and steps on the hole to cover them. 20. Cana Imperial is another improved soilage type grass which appears to do well in some livestock areas of the Andes as shown here near San Cristobal in Tachira. Greater use of improved pastures appears to be desirable development in many areas now used for annual crops but more information on cultural methods practical for the ecological conditions in the Andes is necessary. 21. After the burning process which was previously pictured the land is planted, in this case to corn, without further soil tilling in the shifting cultivation system of farming. The men in the picture are preparing to plant with a planning stick and a mattock for use in the steeper areas. 22. One of the few areas where small, one family livestock farms are prevalent in the Andes is located in the "caserio" of Sabana Grande in the State of Tachira. Pasture production in such high valley areas constitutes a more reasonable land use than annual crop production customary in many other zones with similar land resources. 23. After boiling down the sugar cane juice in from three to five vats the remaining sugar and molasses is molded in square cakes weighing about one pound as shown here. For shipping the panela is wrapped in banana or wild plantain type leaves usually with 96 cakes per pack or "bulto". Two of these packs make a "carga" for mule transport. 24. The outside view of a typical sugar cane trapiche used in the Andean area shows the heavy smokestack and the pile of bagasse which is used as fuel along with wood in the furnace heating the boiling vats. 25. The most frequently used sugar cane trapiche in the Andes is the three roller press pictured here. The sugar cane juice which can be seen coming out of the side of the machine passes through a tube to an adjoining room where the boiling vats are located which reduce the juice to panela. 26. Corn is usually dried before shelling at the house either by hanging the ears on racks as shown or spreading on the ground or hung with the husks on under eaves of houses. 27. Special drying facilities or mechanical shellers are very scarce in the Andes. Livestock care practices on farms are minimal in the Andes and one sees often animals badly infested with "nuche" as that shown here. Inexpensive contrils are known for the flies and the grubs which infest the animals but very few livestock farmers use such control methods and consequently both quality and quantity of livestock and livestock products suffer. 28. In areas where tree and brush growth is old one butting and burning does not clear the land and it must be done a second time. The unburned sticks have been stacked for better drying and the grass has been cut with machetes preparing for a second burning. 29. Planting of improved pasture grasses has been accomplished in several livestock farms in the Andes as illustrated by this field of Guinea Grass in Tachira. However, continuous experimentation to determine and demonstrate best cultural practices and varieties is not being accomplished now. 30. No caption. 31. Exploitation of lumber resources in the Andes is not of great economic importance at the present time. There are a few saw mills that are pictured either in the piedmont areas or some areas in the State of Merida at high altitudes. 32. Coal deposits near Lobatera are utilized to a limited extent by strip mining methods. Very few of the old hand operated mines are operating today. 33. A recently constructed cement plant between Palmira and Lobatera in Tachira is one of the largest industrial plants in the Andes. 34. Tile manufacturing plants with few exceptions are small businesses scattered in rural areas. Some farm people obtain off-farm employment in such plants as pictured here. 35. Andean miller grinds the wheat crop of Chachopo in Merida. The motif of the cross on the primitive apparatus is typical of this extremely religious community. 36. An Andean housewife prepares a meal much in the manner of her primitive forebears. This kitchen of Aristides Cardenas in the village of Flor Marin, is more elaborate than many in rural Venezuela where housewives do the cooking over simple "fogones", wood fires encircled by stones. 37. Skills are passed from one generation to another with the family. 38. Tobacco was one of the first well known expert crops from the Andes as far back as the 16th Century when colonization first started in the area. It is not of major importance economically for the region now but is still grown and processed in much the same way as it was done in colonial times. It is dried under the eaves of houses as shown in the photograph taken in the dry Chama Valley area below Merida. 39. The thatched roof and festoons of dryingtobacco give this Andean cottage a particularly shaggy look. 40. Coloncita is a typical village of the plains area of Tachira, below the Andes which rise sharply a bit farther west. It is located on the new Panamerican highway between La Fria and El Vigia, virgin territory which is being colonized rapidly since it's opening by the road. 41. A convite near San Miguel, locally organized for the purpose of building a camino vicinal. 42. The most frequent pattern of this distribution of the rural population in the Andes is the grouping of small houses into communities. The houses are grouped in the bottom of a valley, on the sides, or on the crest of a mountain and generally constitute a social community. In this photo we see, in the high Chama valley, some houses grouped on an alluvial fan, a very frequent location for the scattered communities of the high valleys of the Andes. 43. The photo shows an example of so-called "nomad farming", a practice common in the Venezuelan Andes. The farmer, who seldom own the lands and merely squats or share-crops, move from land where the soil is leached to another patch and allows that which he formerly farmed to lie fallow for a period. 44. No caption. 45. Demonstration of practices for the conservation of soil at Mucuchies. 46. Of the three crops universally raised by Andean fa
    - CBR, Andean Study (Box 8, Folder 158)
      51. The central market locations in the Andean area have not developed special facilities for parking or loading platform spaces so truck drivers are forced to use congested street areas for loading and unloading agricultural products brought to the market area either for local sale or transshipment to other market areas. The picture shows a street near the Municipal market in San Cristobal. 52. A commercial dry goods store typical of the area and located in a town in the State of Tachira is shown in this picture. Most of the stores in the Andean region are made up on small establishments usually "one-man businesses" characterized by their limited use of capital and the lack of specialization in the commercial and retail functions. 53. The small "pulperia" is the retail outlet me frequently found in the Andes. These stores sell dried and canned foods, hardware, and clothing, tobacco, and numerous other items. These usually have limited stocks and are run by one family. 54. This Mucuchies sheep farmer is carrying his prize to market while his wife leads two others. 55. An Andean street scene in the town of Santo Domingo, high in the mountains of the state of Merida. 56. The millers of Chachopo is a versatile citizenhe spins and weaves the tough fabric for making the familiar Venezuelan "alpargato" or sandal which is worn throughout the country as a sideline to grinding the wheat of his neighbors. 57. This is an old sugar mill still operating at Mendoz Fria in the state of Trijillo. 58. No caption. 59. Among the present Andean huts constructed by the farmers of this high valley of the state of Merida, many are similar to those built by the old Timotes Indians. In spite of strong Spanish influence and the total disappearance of the Indian in the Andes, the pre-Colombian cultural characteristics still maintained in the region are quite noticeable. 60. Clay is also utilized for making vases by hand methods. The photograph shows one of these rudimentary home industries located at La Ovejera, one of the most arid and eroded zones in the Andes, in the Capacho District, State of Tachira. 61. The "unchanging" Andes. 62. Roads have been improved a great deal in the Andes in recent years. However, access roads to many farm areas are still not available so dependence on expensive mule transportation is still necessary. A "recua" of mules laden with coffee and panela are shown entering Bailadores after a day and a half trip from Southern Merida. 63. The Agricultural and Livestock Bank (BAP) is one of the official organizations whose object is to finance farmers through the concession of credit under liberal terms and in adequate amounts required for agricultural production. This photo shows the entrance to a branch of this institution which is established in San Cristobal. 64. At Escaguey on the Chama River above Merida, is located the largest flour mill in the Andes which is a private business engaged in the manufacture of macaroni products in addition to milling flour. 65. Hides are processed into leather at a fairly well mechanized tannery at San Cristobal. The men are shown selecting the finished tanned hides which will be rolled up and sold to various leather working shops mostly in the Andean Area. 66. Slaughter of beef is usually done in Municipo owned slaughter houses. However, in the small villages slaughter for community use is done without any special facilities as show here. As pictured here, the beef was killed, dressed, cut up and sold on the ground with the hide serving as the table and sales counter. All that was left when the picture was taken was the hide and the offal which the owner carried back to his farm. 67. Home conveniences are few in most Andean homes both in the Tropical Valleys in the piedmont areas and in the high cold areas. Pictured are the kitchen facilities in a home in the Uribante Valley area which is not unusual. Many women in all areas of the Andes have to cook over open fires on the floor. Others have a stone platform on which the open fire is built. Others have kerosene stoves whose use has increased in recent years. 68. The minifundial system perpetuates a low level of living. This choza is located on the Loma of San Miguel in Turjillo. 69. On farm marketing is seldom possible on Andean annual crop farms and a great deal of time is expended in taking small lots of products to towns for sale usually to merchants. Pictured is a burro loaded with yucca and corn with two members of farm family going to market. It required a full day for these two persons to market less than Bs 30 worth of product. 70. On farm marketing of vegetables is not practiced to any great extent in the Andes. Mules are used most frequently to carry products to the town markets for sale. Pictured are a group of farmers each with one mule and a load of onions going to the free market at Independencia, Tachira. 71. No caption. 72. A critical need still exists for more access roads from the through trunk highways to farm areas. Pictured is short section of road built by the cooperative action of a group of farmers in Tachira who by the joint expenditure of labor and some funds to construct less than a kilometer of access road were able to reduce greatly the number of mules they had to maintain on their small farms to haul coffee and other products to market. It also made it possible for more of the children in the area to go to school and participate in other community affairs. 73. View of the railroad station at La Fria on the railroad between Encontrados and Estacion Tachira. Even though the value of cargo transported by railroad of the region was important in the past, the competition of trucks has substantially reduced the traffic of merchandize and passengers by this means of transportation. Already the railroad between La Ceiba and Motatan in the State of Trujillo has been paralyzed and abandoned. 74. Due to the opening of new communication routes and the improvement and increase in the number of automotive vehicles, there has been a considerable decrease in freight rates on the roads in the Andean region. However, the lack of total access roads still makes it necessary to transport the agricultural products from many areas by muleback. This reduces and in some cases nullifies the advantages of the Andean economy represented by the progress in ways and means of road transportation. 75. The tannery plant at San Cristobal as shown in this interior view has machinery and vats for handling a significant volume of hides. 76. No caption. 77. Long use of steep slope lands for annual crops has brought about erosion problems which have attracted government programs for control. Pictured are contour stone fences constructed under government sponsorship in a demonstration area near Mucuchies, Merida. Strip cropping with permanent sod crops are usually necessary for soil conservation on slope lands used for annual crops but such is seldom practiced in the Andes. 78. In the foreground to the left may be seen an example of erosion frequently found in the Andean farmland. CBR economists consider that much land now cropped should be turned to pasture, but such conversion requires technical advice and credit. 79. A large number of the rural Andean population still moves about on foot or muleback and continues to use the old roads and bridges which are usually in bad condition. In such a rugged region as the Andes, where roads are still undeveloped and the population scattered through the mountains, mule trails continue to be the most frequent means of communication, although slow and expensive. 80. A primitive Andean bridge crosses a mountain stream near Mucuraba in Merida. 81. Each populated zone in the Andean region has stimulated the development of an urban agglomeration which functions as the political, commercial, and cultural center of the area. The capitals of Tachira and Merida, for example, are together with Valera in Trujillo, the main focus of their own states and the other important populated zones which exist within each state area are secondary center of a part of the State. Tovar, seen in this photo, is a typical example of a secondary urban center which in this case serves as the focus of the western section of the state of Merida. 82. Tovar is a typical Andean town, tile-roofed and clustered around a central plaza with a handsome colonial cathedral. 83. The Free Market at Tachira. Tachira is a busy place on the one day a week it operates. Such free markets are located at nine other locations in the Andes and are sponsored by the Ministry of Agriculture. 84. Road improvements along main routes are shortening the transportation time between the Andes and the large cities in Venezuela. The new road along the Llanos states of Cojedes, Portuguesa and Barinas with a tie-in road to the Transandean highway through Barinitas and Santo Domingo in Merida as shown in this picture is very helpful in this respect. 85. Newly cut roads in steep mountain country are difficult to maintain because of slides and washouts. The section pictured on the Barinitas - Santo Domingo road in Merida paralyzes traffic occasionally creating problems of spoilage of perishable agricultural products. 86. The Transportation highway has been widened and improved in many areas in recent years but the spectacular switchbacks are still necessary on both sides of the high paramo areas. 87. A policy of price and support is operative for a few products in the Andes charged to the Banco Agricola y Pecuario. The illustrated notice was well distributed in areas where Bank agencies were functioning. However, in the case of corn for the 1952 and 1953 crops the Bank was unable to buy all the corn offered because of lack of facilities to handle the corn and many farmers had to take prices almost half the support price to get rid of their crop. 88. Half of the Andean region is still covered with forest and even within the populated areas large extensions of land with little population remain. This aerial photograph of a zone between La Fundation and Los Naranjos, along the Uribante river, represents one of the typical populated areas of low density where the scattered "conucos" and "potreros" leave to the forest at least 50% of the land. 89. In the valley of the Motatan river, near Chachopo, Merida, there are three wheat mills at work. They are rudimentary and of small capacity and this is where the farmers transform their cereal into whole wheat flour before selling it. In payment for their service, the mills take a share of the wheat equivalent to 80% of the total wheat milled (4kgs out of each 50kgs). The photograph shows the primitive stone wheel turned by water power which is used as the grinding device in these mills. 90. The "frailejon" plant is identified with the Andean Paramo areas. Its bunches of silvery white leaves can be seen for great distances. Other planes growing at these high altitudes are all stunted type shrubs and convey the impression of the high areas above 3000 meters altitude and often describe a large part of the Andean area based on this impression. 91. Towns and villages constitute a different type of rural agglomeration but are not too frequent in the Andes. Outside of the municipio capitals these agglomerations are generally few. Situated at strategic points they serve as focus for the farmers who live in the immediate surroundings. As in Peribeca, small village in the Capacho district which appears in this photo, a grouping of this type includes a church, a school, a dispensary and some small commercial establishments. 92. The construction of a road into the San Camilo forest in the southern part of the State of Tachira recently caused a heavy migration of Andean farm families towards these plains at the foot of the mountain range. Begun 10 years ago this road was continued in 1952 and 1953 and it was then that it produced its attraction. As one can see, in the two comparative drawing